A Guide to the H. R. McIlwaine Papers, 1885-1934
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
H. R. McIlwaine Papers, 1885-1934
Library of Virginia
24641
2 cubic feet
H. R. McIlwaine
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Librarian, Virginia State Library and Archives, 1 July 1957.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry Read McIlwaine was born 12 July 1864 in Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Joseph Finley McIlwaine (1838-1897) and Sarah Embry Read McIlwaine (1841-1875). McIlwaine grew up in Petersburg, Virginia, where he attended W. Gordon McCabe's (1841-1920) University School. He graduated with an A.B. from Hampden-Sidney College in 1885 and with a Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1893. McIlwaine taught in private schools for a few years before returning to Hampden-Sidney College to serve as professor of English and history. In 1907, he was appointed State Librarian for the Virginia State Library, which position he held until his death. While Librarian, McIlwaine published several volumes of documents with significant historical value, making them more accessible to scholars. McIlwaine was made an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa by the College of William and Mary in 1909, and received an honorary LL.D. from Hampden-Sidney in 1918. McIlwaine was considered a leading authority on Virginia history and genealogy. Unmarried, he died 16 March 1934 in Richmond, Virginia, and was buried in Blandford Cemetery in Petersburg.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1885-1934, of H. R. McIlwaine (1864-1934), professor of history, English literature, and logic at Hampden-Sidney College and State Librarian of the Virginia State Library, consisting of abstracts, accounts, book reviews, budgets, certificates, clippings, commissions, correspondence, diplomas, exams,invitations, legislation, lists, notes, obituaries, photographs, poems, receipts, reports, resolutions, speeches, and telegrams divided into two series. The first is correspondence, 1885 to 1927, and the second is articles, book reviews, speeches, etc.
Correspondence includes letters written by former students of Hampden-Sidney College on H. R. McIlwaine's behalf to Hampden-Sidney College when he was under investigation by the school in 1904. Also contains letters written on his behalf when McIlwaine was pursuing the position of state librarian of the Virginia State Library in 1907. Of interest is a letter from Woodrow Wilson (1856-1924), president of Princeton University, declining to recommend McIlwaine for the state librarian position. Contains letters from McIlwaine's brothers, James R. McIlwaine (1860-1923) of Nashville, Tennessee, and Richard McIlwaine (1870-1937) of Norfolk, Virginia, concerning family and business matters, including their father's death, James' handling of their financial accounts, and James' death and his estate. Other correspondence details McIlwaine's efforts to find a teaching position, his tenure as a professor at Hampden-Sidney College, and his tenure as state librarian, as well as personal, family, and business matters. Letters also discuss Read and Doak families genealogies, the Seaboard Air Line Railway, and Confederate veteran Isaac Read. Also includes McIlwaine's ph.d. from Johns Hopkins University in 1893 and his honorary degree from Hampden-Sidney College in 1918.
The Articles, Book Reviews, Speeches, etc., series includes reports, speeches, articles, and legislation regarding the Virginia State Library, public libraries in Virginia, and education. Also contains book reviews written by McIlwaine on books about genealogy and American and Virginia history. Also includes articles and speeches written by McIlwaine on famous Virginians and Americans: Thomas Jefferson, Robert E. Lee, John Marshall, Cyrus Hall McCormick, Samuel Preston Moore, Edmund Randolph, and George Washington. Also cotains essays written on the histories of Virginia, Vermont, Texas, Tennessee, Delaware, and Connecticut, along with histories of Buckingham County and Jamestown, Virginia, and the Lost Colony. Of interest are newspaper clippings, 1912-1936, concerning the State Library, including efforts to construct a new building for it in 1931. There are eulogies written on the occasions of the deaths of John S. Patton, W. Pernet Patterson, Edward Virginius Valentine, and H. R. McIlwaine. Also of note are papers concerning the great seal of Virginia and resolutions on the 150th anniversary of the British surrender at Yorktown.
Organization
Collection is divided into two series: Correspondence, 1885-1934 and Articles, Book Reviews, Speeches, etc. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1885-1934 (Box 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1885-1890, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904, March-11July (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1904, 12 July-December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1907, January-19 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1907, 22 June-29 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1907, 1 July- 8 July (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1907, 8 July-17 July (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1907, 25 July-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Articles, Book Reviews, Speeches, etc. (Box 3-4)
  - Bills, Resolutions (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Papers before the Budget Committee (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Report to Governor Pollard, 20 December 1933 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reports of the Library Board and Abstracts (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Work of the Virginia State Library (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Articles or items of special interest in the State Library (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Pre-Revolutionary records of Virginia and their restoration, 31 January 1933 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Virginia fiction in the State Library, 1 July 1911 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Adult education and libraries, 12 February 1932 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The free public library in America (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Libraries in Virginia (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The value of public libraries, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clerks of the Court meeting at Fredericksburg, Virginia, 18 August 1933 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Commission to Stud the Condition of the Farmers of Virginia (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Commission to Survey Educational System, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Classical Association Welcome, 1 December 1933 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Virginia Library Association, Richmond, Virginia, 18 November 1933 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Cooperative Education Association of Virginia (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - On furnishing reading material to soldiers during the World War [I] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Thomas Jefferson as a lover and collector of books, 10-11 November 1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lafayette and Virginia, prepared for Governor Peery (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Radio talk on General Lee, 19 January 1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Presentation of portrait of General John Marshall Jones to R. E. Lee Camp (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cyrus Hall McCormick, for Governor Pollard, 11 July 1931 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Samuel Preston Moore (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Edmund Randolph (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - George Washington's education (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Early history of Buckingham County, Virginia, 30 May 1933 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Connecticut for Governor Byrd, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Delaware, for Governor Byrd, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Religious observances at Jamestown in early days (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sir Walter Raleigh's Lost Colony (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Richmond before 1861 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Notes on the history of Tennessee, for Governor Byrd, 16 September 1929 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Texas and Virginia (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Virginia and Vermont, for Governor Byrd, 16 May 1929 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Story of Virginia's first century, 16 November 1928 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Battle of Monongahela and Virginia, for Governor Pollard, 16 May 1930 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - The Republican Party (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Our Flags of Yesterday and Today (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - The Festal Days of Thanksgiving and Christmas (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - The Huguenot Settlement at Manakin Town, 16 April 1932 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Causes of the War of 1812, Some of Its Incidents, and Its Results (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Great Virginia Tobacco Law of 1790 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - The Conquered Banner (Mrs. Schaadt) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Minutes of the Council and General Court, 31 October 1930 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Book Review, A Doctor of the 1870's and 80's by W. A. Pusey (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Book Review, Charles Parish, York County, Virginia, History and Regsiter by Landon C. Bell (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Book Review, Dissolution of the Virginia Company by Wesley Frank Craven (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Book Review, The Great Awakening in Virginia, 1740-1790 by Wesley M. Gewehr (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Book Review, Hidden Things Brought to Light by Ernest Taylor Walthall (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Book Review, The Iliads of the South by Rosewell Page (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Book Review, John Marshall in Diplomacy and in Law by Lord Craigmyle (John Shaw) (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Book Review, Life of John Taylor by Henry H. Sims (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Book Review, Little Aleck: A Life of Alexander H. Stephens by E. R. Richardson (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Book Review, Medicine in Virginia in the Eighteenth Century by Wyndham B. Blanton (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Book Review, Nicolas Martiau, the Adventurous Huguenot, the Military Engineer, and the Earliest American Ancestor of George Washington by John Baer Stoudt (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Book Review, Our Earliest Colonial Settlements, Their Diversities of Origin, and Later Characteristics by Charles M. Andrews 1933 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Book Review, The Reads and Their Relatives by Alice Read Rouse 1930 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Book Review, Religious Education in the Rural Church by Henry W. McLaughlin (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Book Review, Virginia, Economic and Civil by VPI with the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce 1933 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Book Review, The Washington Ancestry and Records of the McClain, Johnson, and Forty Other Colonial American Families by Charles Arthur Hoppin 1932 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Book Reviews (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1912-1914, 1920-1923 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1931, 1935, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - In Memoriam: John S. Patton (1932), W. Pernet Patterson (1930), Edward Virginius Valentine (1930), and H. R. McIlwaine (1934) (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Hampden-Sidney College Magazine and Hampden-Sidney College Library (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Great Seal, 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - House Document No. 4: Gas Tax Fund Apportionment 1928 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Yorktown Anniversary Resolutions 1931 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Blank Forms (Box 4, Folder 54)